This is Hyen's Lima at his PDP7 with a
teletype and a type 340 vector graphics
display and a light pen showing Pixie
that he developed at Cambridge
University that has one of the first
known uh radial menus operated by a
light pen. So you uh that cursor in the
center is what you can draw with and the
menu items are around the cursor. Also,
there's menu items along the right edge
of the screen to set the different modes
for drawing. And
if you just touch this with the light
pen, that runs the command. And then uh
it tracks by putting these dots on the
screen. Now, see how you can move it
around by dragging the middle. And then
you can pop up the menu to select
different components and the menu
travels along with you. And uh the neat
thing is you can draw a line and then uh
undo it by moving back along the line or
just uh do diagonal lines and attach
things. So this is a general purpose
drawing editor and it's a vector
graphics display with beautiful green
phosphor. Um and uh Hines Hines Lima
here scanned 128 pages of PDP7 assembly
language and we have OCRD it and brought
it back to life here. Let's see.
This is a PDP7 emulator with a type 340
graphics display. Uh now there's a
little bit that we can do since we're
running in the web browser. We can do
this vector graphics display is actually
another CPU that's sharing the memory
with the PDP7 and it draws characters
and lines
and the the user interface can look at
those things and know what they are and
like what code drew them and what how it
gets touched by the light pen. So, um,
if see this little spiral here, see, I
can zoom in here. Um, this if when you
press down and you start moving, it
starts moving along with you. I haven't
done anything yet. It's just a track and
cross. But if you move too fast, it gets
away from you. So, it pops the menu back
up. So, uh, now we can do these
commands. S is to start. Now, that's
changed to F. So, for finish. Now, what
I can do now is draw a line. And this is
for stairst step lines that you'd use
for electrical diagrams. And then oh, if
you don't like that, you can go back.
Whoop. So this see this is what
Schneiderman says about uh direct
manipulation with continuous reversible
actions. So and then you you draw and
then you say, "Oh, I want a capacitor."
Boop. And then you can draw some more
and bring it down here. And look how the
the resistor goes in the direction that
you're going. Resistor
And then like that. And then uh there's
you can finish it. Now that becomes your
your uh circuit there. Maybe we can go
over here and start another one. Uh so
see how the menu
goes away when you're moving
and then comes back. And uh you know
these [laughter] here, let me go back to
normal size. Uh you know there's like a
rubber band. I could finish this boop
and then go into rubber band mode
and I'll bring him over here and I'll
start one and then ah now we're doing a
rubber band. So um like that finish.
Okay. Ah there's some neat things you
can do since we're running this
emulator. Um I'll scroll down a little
bit. So these are uh panels we can
configure. We can pause the CPU or make
it run, you know, maximum 10 times fast
or really slow. Oh, the cool thing is
like Oh, look at that. Oh my god. What
in the world is that? Um, that's
interesting. So, uh, so we're running it
really slow. It's supposed to be
updating its screen really fast, but
this is kind of neat. I'll have to
figure out why it's doing this. Um, but
I've been debugging this code by running
it and finding OCR errors, so you never
know. Um, so let's see. Now, a neat
thing that you can do is play. Gives you
a little demo button and it's just going
to play back some Oh, it's really fast.
I'm at max. Okay, that was not
realistic. Let's just only do it at 10
times.
So, this is driving [clears throat] it
through the light pen. Okay, so um just
do normal one time. So, see how you can
draw and then you draw some more and
then you move up. kind of have to steer
around the stuff that's drawn because it
confuses the tracking. You kind of trip
over it. Um, so yeah, it's I mean it's
very dependent on the way the input
device works. So, uh,
anyway, this is sort of like something
you your child would draw and you hang
on the refrigerator. This was actually
Claude that just came up with these
childlike uh, diagram, but that was
exactly what I wanted. So, um, let's
see. But there are weird things that you
can do since this is a, um, so there's a
TTY. Every good PDP7 should have a TTY.
Hello.
>> Hello.
>> Oh, this one has speech recognition. Um,
help.
It doesn't have any help. Oh, no.
[laughter]
There are other programs.
Um anyway, uh let me turn off the speech
recognition.
Uh so anyway, PDP10 or you know TTY
can't do that, but we can. So uh and it
scrolls. So uh let's see where was I?
Oh, right. Every good computer has
registers. So and this is the front
panel. We're going to make a more
skeworphic thing right now, but we're
just kind of going for green screen. Um,
so the uh Oh, now registers are nice,
but what about memory? Okay, what? Oh my
god, look at this. Okay, this is insane.
Okay, I'm gonna have to pause here.
Um, what we did is we
hind scanned all this code on paper
that we can now single step through. So
this is the original code. This is like
a source map, but it goes two levels. It
goes from memory into lines from source
code and we can even choose the AS7
translation of source code which is a
different dialect of PTB7. So there's
multiple source maps and source maps
that go to the scan and we can uh let's
see okay yes there go nice speed here.
So, so it's it's executing the code and
um we can uh we could just like do a
trace or something like that. But uh
anyway,
what is interesting about this? Um well,
first of all,
memory
has the display list. So, these here are
actually instructions to draw. And
there's this neat little thing I can do.
There's I added like normally you have
one light pin but wow I was added
there's eight light pins. We'll have
like multi-user stuff for you soon. So
you can edit 340 instructions. So what
these are are little drawing commands
and they have relative
uh they you know they only have so many
bits of how far they can move. So when
you draw a long line, see this line is
broken up into smaller lines. And each
of these is only allowed
see he's he's like at the end of the
leash. So uh but what I'm doing is I'm
editing the display instructions in
memory. So look at that. Okay. So see
these this memory has PDP7 code in it
but it also has 340 display instructions
which is movegative -1227
or so so I'm editing the move
instruction and if I go here it'll go up
there and you know it's trying to
disassemble it but um so the the the
idea is this display is a vector
graphics display and I can make a user
interface that just reaches down and
peaks and pokes into memory. Um, and uh,
so why would you want to do that? I
don't know. But um, it it's interesting
to debug your programs. And uh, let's
see. Speaking of which, oh, so we
scanned all this code
and the problem was there were some OCR
errors and then it was like, how do we
make the light pin work? Okay. So, in
1964, Deck published a light pen test.
Bless their furry little hearts. So,
what we can do Oh, yeah. See, that's all
it does. It's very This is so
brutalistic. Okay, we do have a I mean,
and this is Dex. There was actually a
page missing from the code. Um, so we we
we got to recreate that because it was
not too hard to figure out. But the the
thing is oh look see we're we're slowing
it down and you can see it's scanning
out. Um this is just uh
it's either SVG or PNG but the plan is
and Loris Bringhoff has already done
this. [clears throat] We just need to
integrate his code is to have a full uh
web GPU or GL uh phosphor simulator so
you'll have the beautiful fading effect.
Um, and that that's but right now. And
what I want to do is make it slow enough
that you can see the beam scanning out.
That's the goal here. So, but anyway.
So, so now the light pin test normally,
you know, it's just flickering like
this. And I'm going to get out of uh the
thing is, see, this is procedural. So,
there's only really one line. It's just
doing in a loop. Oh my god. Have I have
I screwed it up? Show in memory. Oh, you
see? Um, so, oh, let me show you the
reset button. You You don't want to do
that, but you have to pull it down like
that. Anyway, so we're back. The uh
there's a play demo for this. And the
demos are neat because they tell you
what they're doing. Um, so it's going to
it's going to move the light pin around
and uh test out all the light pin. I
actually found bugs this way,
you know. So, [laughter]
the light pen test was pretty useful.
So, um anyway, not too exciting. Uh more
exciting, more to the point. Let's stop
the play. Um
okay. Oh no, we're stuck in the demo
here.
Oh, no. Play. Stop. Okay. Not the
world's greatest user interface. So,
duel, of course, from 1968.
Oh, see see I'm already I'm in like I'm
in um
see see duel drew the two um spaceships
and I'm not running or well it's running
but nobody's going anywhere yet. So So
let me go uh WD.
So So see it's redrawing the little
thing there but you know you you keep
your same um
Uh oh. And then bam, bam, bam, bam, bam.
Oh I'm not that good at this. Oh,
okay. Ah, so what the cool thing is when
duel ends, it hit a halt instruction. So
the emulator knows it's running duel and
it halts and it can look in the memory
and see like who won and keep a tally
like. So you got this whole outside
state in the emulator that can look in
and do anything. So um that that's how
we got a nice you know otherwise it just
halted. See there's the halt.
There's a halt somewhere
trace. Yeah. Halt. So that's uh but
anyway so that's the duel. Um oh okay.
So I needed to test the TTY. Hello. For
the PDP7 teletype, I think of a number
from 0 to 99. You guess it. Press return
to start.
>> Um
uh return.
>> I am thinking of a number. Your guess
>> 50
your guess.
20.
Well, we got a little
>> 20 your guess.
>> We got a little bounce on the thing
here. But at any rate, high low game,
you know that. And then of course
there's lunar lander.
>> Lander for the PDP7 teletype. You are
500 ft up. Falling at 50 ft a second.
You have 60 units of fuel each second.
Burn from 0 to 30. Time is zero.
Altitude is 500. Speed 1. 0 time is 1,
altitude is 410 time is 2, time is time
is 4, altitude is 380, speed is - 30,
altitude is 34, 7.5, speed is -
6, altitude is 310, speed is -4,
your burn time is 7, altitude is 267,
5, speed is -5,
your burn time is 8, altitude is 220,
speed is 50, fuel is, your burn time is
9, PDP P74.
>> Okay, Mitch Bradley. I told Mitch, "Hey,
I have this PDP7
emulator. It really needs a fourth." And
he whipped one out in one day and it's
great. And it turns out the PDP7 has
this really perfect instruction set for
fourth. Um, so let's see where are we
going here. If we slow this down. Um,
okay. So, oh, and see Mitch being like
the fourth actor that he is, uh, made a
turtle graphics
>> he made a turtle graphics system. Oh,
we're going really slow here. The demo
is not designed to be that slow.
>> 23 + 5. Okay. 40 do 200 FD90 RT loop.
Okay. SQ40 do 200 flower 8 do SQL FL.
Okay.
So anyway, you got
>> star 50 do 400 C. Okay,
>> so the cool thing is
>> CS flower poo 400. Okay,
>> it's fourth and it's turtle graphics and
it's vector graphics and fourth is like
assembling uh you know vector graphics
processor code and then it just makes
all these neat little uh programs to
draw on the screen that you can then
edit like this. So, um, oh, but there's
another thing going on. Pixie.
Oh, wait. We'll do Unix first. Okay.
Hello. Login is Ken.
>> Login.
Ken. Password.
Ken
at
>> Oh, there. LS.
>> LS.
>> Here. We'll make it a little faster.
Like we'll have
>> DD Maxis Soo S1 SS2 SS3 SS4 SS5 SS6 SS7
SS8 S LS
>> system
>> okay a you got all that great stuff
>> APR as BCA cat mod
>> uh
>> oh S1S so there's an assembler there's a
BCPL compiler everything you ever needed
I better oh config here. I'm going to
turn for your sanity we can turn off.
>> Yes. Return lac in one in get a number
of interrupt one source nar zero jmp one
>> off. Okay there that's a little better.
So we have options. So anyway the thing
it does is it run this is the first
version of Unix on a PDP7.
Um so let's go back to Pixie.
So [clears throat and cough] when uh
what it does, this is hard to explain.
Okay, you know like XML, JSON,
YAML, all that stuff. Pixie had a more
general kind of uh way to represent data
that uh it's called rings
uh pixie rings so to speak. And um what
happens is that's different. There's a
different layer than the drawing
instructions. So when I Oops, I better
turn off the drawing editor. [laughter]
Go back to light pin mode. Okay. So in
and turn off the memory. We just have
rings shown. So when I drag this No. No.
Okay. And I start and I draw. This is
kind of in a in a buffer. It's just not
committed yet. But I finish. Ah, so what
this is is a pixie ring, so to speak.
It's it's like lisp conses. It has a
con, a car, and a cutter and and it has
characters and data. And uh when I do
things like
zigzag,
then maybe maybe a capacitor
and uh let's finish that. Okay. See, so
I got some more stuff. This view is just
reading it right out of core memory
18bit core memory live. So, you know,
you can see there's this double
buffering going on because you you don't
see what it's drawing yet.
But then if you commit it,
boop. But then, oh, here we can go play
demo. And now you can see it is drawing
the whole
thing. That's the drawing. So,
so but anyway, so it seemed to be this
is a nice little PDP7 library to do this
that's separate from Pixie. So I
thought, well, why don't we make these
things from Fourth and I linked it in
like this. So there's the TTY. Ah, okay.
So see, Fourth starts out with this
little thing that says,
"Hello world.
from PDP74th.
There we go. So, let me spin it again.
So, Forth can make these too and uh the
it's going to be able to send these back
and forth to Pixie and you can run
several emulators at once and stuff like
that. But, um so, you know, the the
turtle graphics of fourth doesn't really
know about Pixie's drawings. See, the
same way that SVG is an application of
XML, Pixie drawings are an application
of these Pixie rings and that you could
use them to store whatever you wanted,
like a hello world message. So, the
turtle graphics is going to make Pixie
graphics that you could send over to
Pixie and edit in Pixie and then it'll
render that into uh
into drawings. So, so but anyway,
there's um all sorts of ideas here. Um
turtle words and uh let's see.
So, there is this cabinet manifesto. We
control the horizontal. We control the
vertical. The machine in the page is
ours. All of it at once. Every register,
every word of core, every device, the
host around them. Nothing here is a
black box we have to squint at through a
keyhole. So, when something would be
better, we make it better for whichever
side is closest. This 1960s machine
stays honest. Everything around it is
ours to invent. So basically tribute,
accessibility, and fun beat realism.
Okay. So we, you know, we want to list
who made this, where did it come from,
and then we want to make it accessible
for like blind people to use or speech
recognition. So, and then the um anyway,
we're going to we have some more
ambitious plans to model
photorealistically the hardware and even
the people operating it. So,
let's see.
And there's like a little tutorial on
Pixie here. And there is a uh
tutorial here on fourth
how to use the pixie rings and how to do
turtle graphics. See there's these words
to to make things like here. Let's just
do this. Copy this and then go boop like
that. And then we get ah oh look it
it added them. Triangle square hello.
So, so he said
oops okay is not a thing here
like that. So
basically the whole idea is this is a
live coding platform
with data visualization and stuff. So
square square
you could even do Star Wars credits.
Um,
but anyway, uh, let's see.
I think that's enough for now. So, I'm
going to go
Oh, wait. There was Did somebody
I think somebody deleted.
Anyway, well, have fun.